A Guide to the Correspondence and Subject Files of the Virginia Secretary of Transportation, 1972-1982
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Correspondence and Subject Files of the Virginia Secretary of Transportation, 1972-1982
The Library of Virginia
31651
9.9 cu. ft. (11 boxes)
Virginia. Office of the Secretary of Transportation
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Accession 31651 was transfered from the Office of the Secretary of Transportation on 12 January 1983.
Biographical Information
In 1970, the Governor's Management Commission Study recommended the creation of six "Deputy Governors" to assist the Chief Executive in his managerial duties. Compatible functions of government were grouped under these administrative heads, who would serve as the Governors top management team or "secretariats," as they are called now.
Governor Linwood Holton's top priority for the 1972 session of the General Assembly was a proposal for a Governor's Cabinet, reorganizing state agencies into six major departments--each headed by a secretary appointed by the governor. Transportation and public safety was one of these six departments. The office of Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety was created on April 8, 1972, by an act passed by the General Assembly. Governor Holton appointed Wayne A. Whitham, a member of the Winchester City Council, as the first Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety. When Whitham took office on July 1, 1972, he was responsible for State Highway Commission, Division of Motor Vehicles, Department of State Police, Highway Safety Division, Office of Emergency Services, Department of Military Affairs, Virginia State Crime Commission and the Law Enforcement Officers Training Standards Commission. The Office has undergone a series of administrative reorganizations since. On April 12, 1976, the Legislature established separate secretariats for transportation and for public safety, effective July 1, 1976. On July 1, 1984, the offices were again combined. Most recently, the Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety was divided into separate secretariats on February 22, 1990. The Secretary of Transportation is a member of the Governor's Cabinet, and is appointed by the governor, subject to confirmation by the General Assembly. The Secretary is responsible to the governor for the Department of Transportation, Department of Rail and Public Transportation, Department of Aviation, Department of Motor Vehicles, Virginia Port Authority and the Motor Vehicle Dealers Board.
Wayne A. Whitham, the first Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety, was reappointed by Governor-elect Miles E. Godwin, Jr., in December 1973 and by Governor-elect John N. Dalton in December 1977. Whitham suffered a heart attack in August 1978 and resigned in December 1978. On June 7, 1984, Whitham died in Richmond, Virginia. Governor Dalton named George M. Walters, a former top executive of the Reynolds Metals Corporation, to succeed Whitham as Secretary of Transportation. Walters served until the end of Dalton's term in January 1982. Governor-elect Charles S. Robb, the first Democrat to be elected governor since 1965, did not retain any of Dalton's cabinet secretaries. Robb appointed Andrew B. Fogarty, Dalton's assistant secretary for financial policy, as Secretary of Transportation. On July 1, 1984, the secretariats of transportation and public safety were combined again. As a result this partial reorganization of state government, Governor Robb appointed Fogarty Secretary of Administration and Franklin E. White, Secretary of Public Safety, assumed Fogarty's Transportation duties. White, who served as a White House liaison official under President Jimmy Carter, resigned in June 1985 to become the New York state commissioner of transportation. He was replaced by Andrew Fogarty who served until the end of the Robb administration. He later served as Governor Gerald L. Baliles chief of staff from August 1986 to October 1989 when he resigned to become a vice president with CSX Corporation.
In December 1985, Governor-elect Gerald L. Baliles, picked Vivian E. Watts, a northern Virginia legislator, as Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety. Watts served until the end of Baliles' term in 1990. In 1995 she was elected to her old seat in the Virginia House of Delegates. On February 22, 1990, the Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety was divided into separate secretariats. Governor L. Douglas Wilder, appointed John G. Milliken, a member of the Arlington County Board of Supervisors, as the Secretary of Transportation. Milliken resigned on December 17, 1993.
In February 1994 Governor George Allen, the first Republican elected governor since 1977, appointed Robert Martinez as Secretary of Transportation. Martinez was born in Cuba and had served as Deputy Administrator for the Marine Administration and Associate Deputy Secretary of Transportation during President George H.W. Bush's administration. At the end of Governor Allen's term in January 1998, Martinez joined the Norfolk Southern Corporation. Shirley Ybarra, deputy Secretary of Transportation in the Allen administration, was named Martinez's successor by Governor-elect James Gilmore. Ybarra previously worked as a special assistant to Transportation Secretary Elizabeth Dole during President Ronald Reagan's administration. Ybarra served until the end of Gilmore's administration in January 2002. Whittington W. Clement, a former lawyer and long-time member of the Virginia House of Delegates representing the City of Danville, was appointed Secretary of Transportation by Governor Mark R. Warner in 2002. Pierce R. Homer, Deputy Secretary of Transportation, replaced Clement in 2005.
Scope and Content
Contains files pertaining to Virginia transportation concerns, including but not limited to the Energy, Interstate, and Rails. This collection contains; correspondence and subject files, as well as, Committee and Commission files, Legislation, Regulations.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Correspondence and Subject Files
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence and Subject Files, 1972-1982., Extent: 11 boxes. (Box 1-11)
  This collection is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Architectural Barriers: Task Force (Rehabilitation Act of 1973), 1973. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Aviation: Virginia Air Transportation Systems Study, 1977-1979. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Blacksburg, Town of: Public Transportation System, 1979. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bus Transportation, 1973-1980. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cabinet: Background Papers, 1973. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Cabinet: Missions and Goals, 1973. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Co., 1976. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - C and C: Chessie/Seaboard Merger, 1978-1979. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Council of Governments: Steering Committee, 1978-1979. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Craigie, Walter, Jr., 1977. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Deaf, Virginia Council for the, 1978-1980. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Defense Depatment, U.S., 1977. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Developmental Disabilities Planning Council, 1980. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Disaster Assistance, 1978. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Dulles International Airport, 1977. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Dynalectron Corporation, 1980. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Eastern Airlines, 1979. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Eastern Shore of Virginia, 1973. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Eastern Shore of Virginia: Seafood Festival, 1978. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Electric-Powered Motor Vehicles, 1980-1981. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Emergency Medical Services, 1980. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Emergency Medical Services: Wachapreague Rescue Squad, 1979. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Emergency Services, 1980. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Emergency Services (Personnel), 1979. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Emergency Services: Jones, George L., 1974-1980. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Energy: Coal - Converting, 1979-1981. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Energy: Conversion of non-state owned oil heating to coal/gas, 1979. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Energy: Conversion of state owned oil heating to coal/gas, 1979-1980. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Energy: Dalton Statement on Energy, 1979. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Energy: Dalton Orders, 1979. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Energy: Emergency energy conservation act of 1979 (federal), 1979. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Energy: Position Paper/Virginia buisness council on energy for the commonwealth, 1980-1981. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Energy: Schools, hospitals, local governments/public care grants, 1979. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Energy: U.S. department of, 1974-1980. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Energy: Wood Project, 1979-1980. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Executive Orders, 1978. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Governor's Council on Transportation, 1978-1979. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - House Roads and Internal Navigation Committee (Ga.), 1977. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Information Committee, 1973-1979. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Intergovernmental Statewide Affairs, department of - Cost Allocation, 1980. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Intergovernmental Affairs: National Governor's Association, 1979. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Intergovernmental Affairs, Department of, 1977-1980. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Interior Department, U.S., 1975-1980. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - International Business Machines, 1974-1976. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Interstate 64, 1972-1980. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Interstate 6-64, 1977-1980. (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Interstate 66, 1977-1980. (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Interstate 81, 1978-1980. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Inrvington, Town of, 1979-1980. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - James River Limestone Co., 1980. (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - joint Legislation Audit Review Commission (JLARC: Land Management), 1980. (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Labor, U.S. Department of,. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Local Government Advisory Council,. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Logo Signing: Highway, Travel Service,. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Loudon County,. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Dolley Madison: Birthplace Dedication, Greensboro, N.C.,. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Management Analysis and Systems Development, Department of,. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Metropolitan Planning Organization: Redesignations,. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Metropolitan Planning Organizations: Designations,. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Metropolitan Planning Organizations,. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - mileage Reports: Energy Conservation,. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous,. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Motor Vehicles, Division of,. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Norfolk, City of,. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Parks, State Division of, 1973-1978. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Peninsula Transportation District Commission, 1977-1979. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Personnel: Revised Salary, 1979. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Piedmont Traffic Club: "Carriers Nite", 1977-1978. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Pollution: State Air Pollution Control Board, 1975-1978. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Population: Northern Virginia, 1979. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Precious metals Legislation, 1980-1981. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Prince William County: Manassas, 1975-1979. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Printing: See: Purchases and Supplies, 1974-1977. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Procurement, 1980. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Public Works and Transportation Committee, 1975-1979. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Rail: Commuter Rail Feasibility Study (House Joint Resolution 54), 1974. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Rail: Commuter Rail Service (general), 1978. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Rail: Federal Railroad Administration, 1978-1980. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Rail: Legislation Railroads, 1978-1980. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Rail: Seaboard Coastline, 1974-1980. (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Republican Governor's Association and Republican National Committee, 1980. (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Ridesharing, 1976-1979. (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Richmond: Interstate 295, 1976-1978. (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Savings bonds: 1981 Virginia State Employees Campaign, 1981. (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Selective Service Systems, 1977-1980. (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Senate Transporation Committee, 1977. (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Tidewater Transporation District Commission, 1973-1978. (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Tires: (Retread) State Vehicles, 1980. (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Trailways Bus, 1978-1979. (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Transportation: Daily Correspondence - January-December, 1980. (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Travel: Whitham, Wayne A., 1973-1978. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Transportation Saftey Department: Creation of the Department, 1978. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Transportation Saftey, Department of, 1973-1978. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Transportation, Secretary of, 1973-1978. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Travel Vouchers, 1973-1978. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - United Giver's Fund Campaign, 1980. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - United Nation's Day: Chairman Virginia, 1973-1978. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - United Way Finance Committee, 1973-1978. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Urban Mass Trasportation Administration, 1973-1978. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - U.S. Congressional Correspondence, 1973-1978. (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Virginia Asphalt Association, Inc., 1973-1978. (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Virginia Council on State Legislation, 1973-1978. (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Virginia Port Authority, 1973-1978. (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Virginia Road and Transportation Builder's Association, 1973-1978. (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State university: President, 1973-1978. (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Washington, DC: Misc., 1973-1978. (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Williamsburg, Virginia, 1973-1978. (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Winchester, Virginia, 1973-1978. (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Yorktown Victory Campaign: October, 1981. (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Appropriations Committee, 1980-1982. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Amendments to 1980 Appropriation Act, 1980-1982. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Budget: General, 1980-1982. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Budget Guidance: goals, objectives, and Policies, 1980-1982. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Capital Outlay, 1980-1982. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Addendum Request, 1980-1982. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Secretary of Transportation, 1980-1982. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Department of Aviation, 1980-1982. (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Emergency and Energy Services, 1980-1982. (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Request for Exceptions, 1980-1982. (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Highways and Transportation, Department of, 1980-1982. (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Budget: Department of Military Affairs, 1980-1982. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Budget: Request for Exceptions - Department of Military Affairs, 1980-1982. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Budget: Department of Motor Vehicles Program Proposal and Budget Exhibit, 1980-1982. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Budget: Department of Motor Vehicles, 1980-1982. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Budget: Department of Motor Vehicles - Request for Exceptions, 1980-1982. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Budget: Department of Transportation Safety, 1980-1982. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Budget: Department of Transportation Safety - Request for Exceptions, 1980-1982. (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Budget: Virginia Port Authority - Request for Exceptions, 1980-1982. (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Budget: Virginia Port Authority - Program Proposal and Budget Exhibit, 1980-1982. (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Budget: Appropriations Act Ammendments, 1978-1980. (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Budget: Ammendments - Appropriations Act, 1978-1980. (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Budget: Budget Bill, 1978-1980. (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Budget: Budget General, 1978-1980. (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Transportation Planning Support, 1978-1980. (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Budget, 1978-1980. (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Budget: Exhibit Work Folder, 1978-1980. (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Budget: Exhibit Work Folder, 1978-1980. (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Agency Target Appeal, 1978-1980. (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Allotment Request and Advice, 1978-1980. (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Sum Sufficient Account, 1978-1980. (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Transportation and Public Safety, 1978-1980. (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Budget, 1976-1978. (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Budget: Expenditures, 1978-1980. (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Capital Outlay: General, 1978-1980. (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Capital Outlay: Progress Reports (Quarterly), 1978-1980. (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - General, 1978-1980. (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Budget: Assessment of the Commonwealth, 1978-1980. (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Appropriations Committee Digest, 1978-1980. (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Appropriations Committee Presentation, 1978-1980. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Goals, Objectives, Policies and Program Priorities, 1978-1980. (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Issue Indent and Analysis, 1978-1980. (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Commonwealth Accounting, 1978-1980. (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Federal General Sharing Funds, 1978-1980. (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Governor's Budget Advising Committee, 1978-1980. (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Airport Authority, 1978-1980. (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Aviation, Department of, 1978-1980. (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Financial Information Regarding Department of Aviation, 1978-1980. (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Central Garage Carpool, 1978-1980. (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Agency Target Appeal, 1978-1980. (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Emergency Services, State Office of, 1978-1980. (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Emergency Services, State Office of Budget, 1978-1980. (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Motor Vehicles, Division of, 1978-1980. (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Highways and Transportation, Department of, 1978-1980. (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Agency Target Appeal, 1978-1980. (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Virginia Department of Highway and Transportation: $35 Million, 1978-1980. (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Military Affairs, Department of, 1978-1980. (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Agency Target Appeal: Department of Military Affairs, 1978-1980. (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Virginia Port Authority, 1978-1980. (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Department of Transportation and Safety, 1978-1980. (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Northern Virginia Transportation Commission, 1978-1980. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Agency Target Appeal, 1978-1980. (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Washington Metro Area Transit Commission, 1978-1980. (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Other Agencies Founder, 1978-1980. (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Current Working Papers, 1978-1980. (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Appropriations and Finance Committee, 1978-1980. (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Program Budgeting Process, 1978-1980. (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Highway Construction and Maintenance, 1978-1980. (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Virginia Department of Transportation - Statement of Income and Expenditures, 1978-1980. (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Department of Planning and Budget: Memoranda, 1978-1980. (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Department of Planning and Budget: Forms - DPB 8, 1978-1980. (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Department of Planning and Budget: Forms - DPB 8A, 1978-1980. (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - department of Planning and Budget: Forms - DPB 16, 1978-1980. (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Department of Planning and Budget: Forms - Advice of Allotment, 1978-1980. (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Biennial: Virginia Airport Authority, 1976-1978. (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Biennial: Office of Emergency Services, 1976-1978. (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Biennial: Department of Motor Vehicles, 1976-1978. (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Biennial: Virginia Department of Highways and Transportation, 1976-1978. (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Biennial: Department of Military Affairs, 1976-1978. (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Biennial: Virginia Port Authority, 1976-1978. (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Traffic Records Committee, 1976-1978. (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Traffic Records Information Sysytem - 3, 1976-1978. (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Traffic Records Information Sysytem - 2, 1976-1978. (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Traffic Records Information Sysytem - 1, 1976-1978. (Box 9, Folder 22)
- National Transportation Study, 1972-1974., .45 cu. ft. (1 box) (Box 10)
  - General Correspondence, 1972-1973. (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, 1974. (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - National Transit Study #1, 1974. (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - National Transit Study #2, 1974. (Box 10, Folder 4)
- National Transportation Study, 1972-1974., .45 cu. ft. (1 box) (Box 11)
  - National Transit Study, 1974. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - National Transit Study Addendum, 1974. (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Changes Agaisnt Contract, 1973-1974. (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Contract and Budget Amendments, 1972-1974. (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Contract Negotiation, 1972. (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Financial Reports (Division of State Planning and Community Affairs), 1973-1974. (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Financial Reports (Va. Department of Highways), 1973-1974. (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Grant Payments, 1972-1974. (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Policy Advisory Committee, 1973-1974. (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Work Program, 1972-1974. (Box 11, Folder 10)